Cruiser Houston Collection, 1917-2003
University of Houston Libraries
- STATEMENTS, 1945-1950
  - Leon W. Rogers, undated (photocopy). (Box 16, Folder 30)
  - Albert L. Rooks casualty affidavit, [ca. 1945], (photocopy) (Box 16, Folder 31)
  - K. L. Shaw, USMC, undated (photocopy). (Box 16, Folder 32)
  - Charles D. Smith, September 18, 1945 (photocopy) (Box 16, Folder 33)
  - Charles D. Smith, September 18, 1945 (photocopy). (Box 16, Folder 34)
  - Charles D. Smith, undated (photocopy). (Box 16, Folder 35)
  - John Bell Stivers, undated (photocopy). (Box 16, Folder 36)
  - M. E. Weller casualty affidavits, [ca. 1945], (photocopies) (Box 16, Folder 37)
  - Unidentified, [ca. 1945?] (photocopy) (Box 16, Folder 38)
- ROSTERS, 1942-1998
  The rosters in this series are sorted alphabetically by the type of people listed, such as crew members from the USS Houston (CA-30), Lost Battalion Association members, or prisoners-of-war.
  - Crew members (Exchange of Information Sheet), compiled by Fred G. Hodge, 1946. (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Crew members, compiled by Bill Weissinger, 1983 (photocopy). (Box 17, Folder 2)
    Donor: Bill Weissinger
  - Crew members, compiled by Bill Weissinger, annotated, 1983-1991 (photocopy). (Box 17, Folder 3)
    Donor: Judy L. Robinson
  - Crew members, killed or wounded during the Battle of the Flores Sea, undated. (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - Crew members, 1955. (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - Crew members, 1958. (Box 17, Folder 6)
    Donor: Marvin E. Robinson
  - Crew members, undated (photocopy). (Box 17, Folder 7)
  - Lost Battalion Association members, 1976, with letter from Crayton R. Gordon, April 1976. (Box 17, Folder 8)
  - Lost Battalion Association members, 1983. (Box 17, Folder 9)
  - POWs, Camp No. 11, Americans in Manila Port area, 1942-1944. (Box 17, Folder 10)
  - POWs, Camp Omori, Tokyo, Japan, August 1945 (photocopy). (Box 17, Folder 11)
  - POWs, deceased, American personnel, Fifth Branch Burma, undated (photocopy). (Box 17, Folder 12)
  - POWs, deceased, Americans in Capt. Fitzsimmons’ party and Col. Tharp’s party, 1944. (Box 17, Folder 13)
  - POWs, deceased, undated. (Box 17, Folder 14)
  - POWs, deceased, undated (carbon copy). (Box 17, Folder 15)
  - POWs, USS Houston (CA-30), compiled by John C. Reas, [ca. 1942-1945], signed 1998 (photocopy), with letter from John C. Reas, April 26, 1998. (Box 17, Folder 16)
  - POWs, USS Houston (CA-30), compiled by John C. Reas, [ca. 1942-1945], with photograph of John C. Reas, 1940(printed digital copies, matted). (Ovs OVS)
  - POWs, USS Houston (CA-30), enlisted personnel and locations as POWs, [ca. 1942-1945]. (Box 17, Folder 17)
  - POWs, USS Houston (CA-30), [ca. 1942-1945]. (Box 17, Folder 18)
  - POWs (with details on health, movements, and financial transactions), 1943. (Ovs OVS)
  - USS Houston Survivors mailing list, 1959. (Box 17, Folder 19)
- POW CAMP RECORDS, 1942-1945
  This series includes original records that were created in the prisoner-of-war camps. One set of records was created at the hospital where the POWs were treated following their liberation. Many of these records are extremely fragile.
  Additional information related to the POW camps may be found in the Rosters series.
  - Information regarding [POW] casualties…gathered from…POWs at 142nd General Hospital, Calcutta, 1945 (Box 17, Folder 18)
  - Henry Nickel record, [1942-1945], (photocopy). (Box 17, Folder 19)
  - Lawrence Kondzela record, Japanese, [1942-1945], (photocopy). (Box 17, Folder 20)
  - No. 3 Branch, Thai POW camps, relationship of number of deaths to strength, by forces, [ca. 1942-1945]. (Box 55, Folder 1)
  - Frank Pistole record, [1942-1945], (photocopy). (Box 17, Folder 21)
  - POW casualties in Thailand and Burma to April 1944, [ca. 1944]. (Box 17, Folder 22)
  - POW death reports, three, 1943 (photocopies). (Box 17, Folder 23)
  - POW service records for USS Houston crew members (includes records of locations, illnesses, and deaths), 1942-1945. (Box 17, Folder 24)
    Donor: John Harrell
  - POW work records, [1942-1945]. (Box 17, Folder 25)
    Donor: Jack Smith
- CITATIONS, 1942-1949
  This series includes citations and other commendations for military service, arranged alphabetically by recipient.
  - George E. Detre, Thank You letter from Harry Truman, [ca. 1945] (photocopy). (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - Memorandum for Recipients of Prisoner of War Medal, March 1, 1988. (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - Henry Nickel, Bronze Star Medal Citation, [ca. 1947], with letter from the Chief of Naval Personnel, November 3, 1947. (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - Henry Nickel, Commendation Ribbon Citation, [ca. 1947]. (Box 18)
  - Henry Nickel, USS Houston (CA-30) Presidential Unit Citation, [ca. 1942]. (Box 18)
  - Albert H. Rooks, Chevalier in the Military Willemsorde, February 20, 1948, with letter from F. Stam to Edith R. Rooks, Washington D.C., January 10, 1949. (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - Albert H. Rooks, Congressional Medal of Honor Citation, [ca. 1942]. (Box 18)
  - Albert H. Rooks, Medal of Honor Citation, [ca. 1942]. (Box 18)
  - Albert H. Rooks, USS Houston (CA-30) Presidential Unit Citation, [ca. 1942]. (Box 18)
  - Albert H. Rooks, Press Release for Congressional Medal of Honor, June 24, 1942 (photocopy) (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - USS Houston Ship’s Company, Presidential Citation, [ca. 1942] (photocopy). (Box 18)
- CERTIFICATES, 1924-1998
  The certificates in this series, which are primarily for military or educational achievements, are arranged alphabetically by recipient.
  - William C. Batchelor, Jr., Purple Heart, March 30, 1998 (photocopy), with request for military records. (Box 18, Folder 6)
  - William C. Batchelor, Jr., various, 1934-1939. (Box 18, Folder 7)
  - George E. Detre, Navy Training Course, August 26, 1941. (Box 18, Folder 8)
  - Frank D. Ellis, various, 1924-1937. (Box 18, Folder 9)
  - Henry Nickel, various, 1933-1990s. (Box 18, Folder 10)
  - USS Rentz Plank Owner Certificate, 1984. (Box 55, Folder 5)
    Donor: USS Houston Survivors Association>
  - Robert G. Vaughn, Jr., Houston Volunteers, May 30, 1942. (Box 68)
    Donor: Estate of Robert G. Vaughn, Jr.
  - Fred Viskovich, Navy Training Course, April 20, 1936. (Box 18, Folder 11)
- PROGRAMS, 1930-2003
  Programs are arranged alphabetically by their title or by the subject of the event.
  - Boxing & Wrestling Finals, February 3, 1940. (Box 18, Folder 12)
  - Christening and Launching Ceremony, USS Rentz (FFG-46), July 16, 1983. Includes photo Christmas card (Box 18, Folder 13)
  - Christmas 1936, USS Houston (CA-30), 1936 (Box 18, Folder 14)
  - Christmas 1936, USS Houston (CA-30), 1936. (Box 18, Folder 15)
    Donor: I. Roy Coats
  - Class of 1914 Dedication Ceremony, United States Naval Academy, Memorial in memory of Captain Albert Harold Rooks, September 24, 1960. (Box 18, Folder 16)
  - Commissioning of the Nuclear Powered Attack Submarine USS Houston (SSN-713), September 25, 1982. (Box 18, Folder 17)
  - Cruiser Houston Memorial Exhibit and the George R. Brown Room Dedication, 1981 (Box 18, Folder 18)
  - Dedication of an Historical Marker at the site of The Induction Ceremony of the Second Cruiser Houston, November 11, 1974. (Box 18, Folder 19)
  - Dedication of the USS Houston (CA 30) Memorial Monument, November 11, 1995. (Box 18, Folder 20)
  - Divine Service, USS Houston, October 6-26, 1935. (Box 18, Folder 21)
  - 50th Anniversary of the Loss of HMAS Perth and USS Houston, Memorial Service & Dedication Ceremony, February 27, 1992. (Box 18, Folder 22)
  - Hawaiian Happy Hour, May 1, 1937. (Box 18, Folder 23)
  - HMAS Perth, 43rd Annual Memorial Service, March 1, 1992,with two items. (Box 18, Folder 24)
  - Homeward Bound, USS Houston, November 7, [1933?] (Box 18, Folder 25)
  - Lost Battalion Association Memorial Dedication, May 4, 1994. (Box 18, Folder 26)
  - Lost Battalion, 12th Annual State Convention, August 10-11, 1956. (Box 18, Folder 27)
  - Presentation to the USS Houston of a Silver Service, October 27, 1930. (Box 18, Folder 28)
    Donor: Estate of Gladys (Patterson) Wilkins
  - Presentation to the USS Houston of a Silver Service, October 27, 1930 (two copies). (Box 18, Folder 29)
    Donor: Ed Wilkins
  - Presidential Cruise Divine Service, July 17-31, 1938. (Box 18, Folder 30)
  - Prince’s [nightclub], Calcutta, September 11, 1945. (Box 18, Folder 31)
  - Radio broadcast, Presidential Cruise, August 6, 1938. (Box 18, Folder 32)
  - San Jacinto Celebration, April 20-21, 1960 (Box 18, Folder 33)
  - Service of Remembrance, USS Houston (CA-30), Norfolk Naval Station, February 27, 1977. (Box 18, Folder 34)
  - 30th Year After Sinking USS Houston (CA-30) Memorial Program, Battleship Texas, February 27, 1972. (Box 18, Folder 35)
  - USS Fort McHenry, Change of Command Ceremony, June 9, 1993. (Box 18, Folder 36)
  - USS Houston Discharge Ceremony, [ca. 1945-1946]. (Box 18, Folder 37)
    Donor: Roy W. Offerle
  - USS Houston Second Presidential Cruise, 1935(printed digital copy). (Box 18, Folder 38)
  - USS Houston Survivors and Next Generation Memorial Service, 1997-2003 (Box 18, Folder 39)
  - USS Houston Survivors Association, 1974 Reunion, April 20-21, 1974. (Box 18, Folder 40)
  - USS Houston Survivors Memorial Ceremony, USS Houston (SSN-713), March 1, 1992 (Box 18, Folder 41)
  - USS Houston (SSN-713), Change of Command Ceremony, May 5, 1995, with invitation and guest pass. (Box 18, Folder 42)
  - USS Houston (SSN-713), Welcoming Ceremony, March 19, 1983. (Box 18, Folder 43)
  - USS McCluskey (FFG-41), Battle of Java Sea-Sunda Strait, 50th Anniversary Commemoration, March 1, 1992 (Box 18, Folder 44)
  - USS McCluskey (FFG-41), Welcome Aboard, [ca. 1992] (Box 18, Folder 45)
- BOOKLETS AND PAMPHLETS, 1934-1997
  Booklets and pamphlets are arranged alphabetically by their creator, title, or subject.
  - The American Battle Monuments Commission, WWII Commemorative Program, undated. (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - Australia’s National Memorial to America, undated (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - Claims Committee, Liberated Military Personnel (Japan), Civil Responsibility of Japan…, 1946. (Box 19, Folder 3)
  - Cruisers Houston Memorial and Cruiser Houston Room [not built], 1976 (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - Death Becomes the Ghost (documentary film), [ca. 1997]. (Box 19, Folder 5)
    Donor: Vic Campbell
  - General Information for visit of U.S. Fleet to Norfolk, Virginia, 1934. (Box 19, Folder 6)
  - The Geneva Convention and You, Armed Forces Talk, December 19, 1952. (Box 19, Folder 7)
  - Glad To Have You Aboard, USS Rooks (DD-804), [ca. 1957] (Box 19, Folder 8)
  - Houston Documentary Expedition, June 1977 (Box 19, Folder 9)
  - Launching Houston (SSN-713), March 21, 1981. (Box 19, Folder 10)
  - Launching Houston (SSN-713), March 21, 1981. (Box 19, Folder 11)
  - Memories (photocopy), undated. (Box 19, Folder 12)
  - Presidential Cruise Aboard the USS Houston, 1934 (photocopy). (Box 19, Folder 13)
  - Remembering the USS Houston [exhibit catalog], University of Houston Libraries, January 15-May 2, 1997 (Box 19, Folder 14)
  - Saga of a Stout Ship, reprinted from Hanson W. Baldwin’s Sea Fights and Shipwrecks; True Tales of the Seven Seas (Box 19, Folder 15)
  - Saga of a Stout Ship, reprinted from Hanson W. Baldwin’s Sea Fights and Shipwrecks; True Tales of the Seven Seas (Box 19, Folder 16)
  - Third Presidential Cruise of the USS Houston, 1938. (Box 19, Folder 17)
    Donor: Harry T. Kelley
  - Third Presidential Cruise of the USS Houston, 1938. (Box 19, Folder 18)
  - USS Houston (CA-30) Porthole, [ca.1992]. (Box 19, Folder 19)
  - USS Houston (CA-30) Ship's Bell, May 1, 1996. (Box 19, Folder 20)
  - USS Houston Ceremony [Ship’s bell], Jakarta, Indonesia, August 24, 1973. (Box 19, Folder 21)
  - USS Houston: From December 8, 1941 Until She Was Reported Missing February 28, 1942, [1942-1945]. (Box 19, Folder 22)
    Donor: Otto Schwarz >
  - USS Houston: From December 8, 1941 Until She Was Reported Missing February 28, 1942, [1942-1945]. (Box 19, Folder 23)
  - USS Houston (CA-30), Monument to Honor the Ship and Her Gallant Crew, November 11, 1995. (Box 19, Folder 24)
  - USS Houston Survivors Association 50th Anniversary Tour, 1992. (Box 19, Folder 25)
  - USS Rentz, undated (Box 19, Folder 26)
  - Lloyd V. Willey, Battle Cruise of the Flagship “Houston,” Sinking of the Flagship “Houston,” Down Below, 1951, with letter from Lloyd Willey to Jack [Smith], April 18, 1953. (Box 19, Folder 27)
  - Lloyd V. Willey, Battle Cruise of the Flagship “Houston,” Sinking of the Flagship “Houston,” Down Below, 1951. (Box 19, Folder 28)
    Donor: Lloyd V. Willey
  - Lloyd V. Willey, For All That She Stood For, January 1984. (Box 19, Folder 29)
  - Lloyd V. Willey, The Last Days of the USS Houston, undated (Box 19, Folder 30)
  - Lloyd V. Willey. Lost Battalion - USS Houston Poem Book, 1983. (Box 19, Folder 31)
    Donor: Jo Burge
  - Lloyd V. Willey. Lost Battalion - USS Houston Poem Book, 1983. (Box 19, Folder 32)
  - Welcome Aboard the USS Houston, [1934] (two copies). (Box 19, Folder 33)
  - Welcome Aboard the USS Houston, July 3, 1935 (two copies). (Box 19, Folder 34)
  - Welcome Aboard, USS Houston (SSN-713), undated. (Box 19, Folder 35)
  - Welcome Aboard, USS Rentz (FFG-46), undated (Box 19, Folder 36)
- DOCUMENTS, 1929-1995
  Documents are arranged alphabetically by their title or subject.
  - American Ex-POWs, California State Department, 1959. (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - American Ex-POWs, Santa Clara Valley Chapter, minutes and correspondence, 1953-1957. (Box 26, Folder 10)
  - American Ex-POWs, Santa Clara Valley Chapter, various, 1953-1960. (Box 20, Folder 2)
  - William C. Batchelor, Jr., miscellaneous documents, 1940-1943. (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - Battle of Sunda Strait, undated (Box 20, Folder 4)
  - Bibliography, USS Houston Survivors Association, [ca. 1980s] (photocopy). (Box 20, Folder 5)
  - (George R.) Brown Room and Cruiser Houston Memorial Exhibit Proposal, ca. 1980-81. (Box 20, Folder 6)
  - Damage control card, 1936. (Box 20, Folder 7)
  - Death certificate, claims, William C. Batchelor, 1945-1946. (Box 20, Folder 8)
  - Death gratuity vouchers, 1945. (Box 20, Folder 9)
  - De Slag in de Javazee (documentary film), promotional materials, ca. 1995 (Box 20, Folder 10)
  - Documents, correspondence, Fort Union Military Academy, William C. Batchelor, 1938-1940. (Box 20, Folder 11)
  - Documents, Mr. and Mrs. Frank Ellis, 1939-1948. (Box 20, Folder 12)
  - Help Us Build a Memorial to Honor the USS Houston (CA 30), 1994. (Box 20, Folder 13)
  - History of the USS Houston (CA-30) Monument, ca. 1990s. (Box 20, Folder 14)
  - HMAS Perth Guided Missile Destroyer, undated (Box 20, Folder 15)
  - House Rules for War Prisoners, Camp at Thanbuzayat, Burma, 1942 (photocopy from Navy Dept.) (Box 20, Folder 16)
  - Houston Volunteers monument, 1985 (Box 20, Folder 17)
  - Inscription for a shrine to the USS Houston (CA 30), by Samuel Milner, with revision, undated (includes photocopies). (Box 20, Folder 18)
  - Inscription for a shrine to the USS Houston (CA 30), by Samuel Milner, undated. (Box 20, Folder 19)
  - Instruction card, water and gas tight closures, 1940. (Box 20, Folder 20)
  - Leaflet announcing end of war, Indochina, September 4, 1945. (Box 20, Folder 21)
  - Leaflets announcing Japanese surrender, 1945 (photocopies). (Box 20, Folder 22)
  - Liberation and Evacuation of Allied Prisoners of War and Civilian Internees in Japan, September 2, 1945. (Box 20, Folder 23)
  - Military Records for Ellis B. Hostick, 1938-1940, with letter, April 5, 1978 (photocopies). (Box 20, Folder 24)
  - Monument Designation ICO USS Houston (CA-30), 1992. (Box 20, Folder 25)
  - National Memorial Cemetery of the Pacific “Punchbowl” plaque design, [1990]. (Box 20, Folder 26)
  - National Memorial Cemetery of the Pacific “Punchbowl” plaque, [ca. 1994]. (Box 20, Folder 27)
  - One Hundred Forty-Eighth Field Artillery, Unit History, 1940-1946 (photocopy). (Box 20, Folder 28)
  - Orders for the Day, March 28, 1938. (Box 20, Folder 29)
  - Orders for the Day, January 3, 1939 (Box 20, Folder 30)
  - Orders for the Day, May 10, 1940. (Box 20, Folder 31)
    Donor: William Ingram
  - Orders for the Day, May 14, 1941, June 4, 1941 (photocopies). (Box 20, Folder 32)
  - Orders for the Day, May 14, 1941 (photocopy). (Box 20, Folder 33)
  - Radio broadcast typescripts, Batavia, Java, March 7, 1943 (photocopies). (Box 20, Folder 34)
  - Radio broadcast typescripts, Batavia, Java, March 7, 1943. (Box 20, Folder 35)
  - Report cards, William C. Batchelor, 1929-1937. (Box 20, Folder 36)
  - Resolution, H.S. Strickland Day, June 30, 1976 (photocopy). (Box 20, Folder 37)
  - Resolution, USS Houston Week, November 6, 1974 (photocopy). (Box 20, Folder 38)
  - Retirement and benefits for Henry Nickel, 1948-1980. (Box 20, Folder 39)
  - Rules for P.O.W.s in Japanese Camps, compiled by Pvt. H.G. Teel and Cpl. Bankhead of 131st F.A. Bn., undated (photocopy) (Box 20, Folder 40)
  - Specifications of USS Houston (SSN-713), 1982. (Box 20, Folder 41)
  - USS Houston/HMAS Perth Memorial, guest list, 1992. (Box 20, Folder 42)
  - USS Houston Morning Press, July 14, 1941. (Box 20, Folder 43)
    Donor: W.W. Daniels
  - USS Mount Vernon deck log, March 1942 (photocopy). (Box 20, Folder 44)
  - USS Tulsa deck log, February 1942 (photocopy). (Box 20, Folder 45)
  - War claims, Henry Nickel, 1946-1956. (Box 20, Folder 46)
  - Watch list (last day in Japan), 1945. (Box 20, Folder 47)
- NEWSLETTERS, 1930-1996
  Newsletters are arranged alphabetically by the name of the organization that created them.
  - Ex-Prisoners of War and Relatives' Association, News Bulletin, 1992-1996 (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - Ex-Prisoners of War Association of Australia, Barbed Wire and Bamboo, 1981-1996. (Box 21, Folder 2)
  - Lost Battalion Association, May/June 1983, November 1983. (Box 21, Folder 3)
  - Naval Air Station, South Weymouth, MA, Navy Family, March 1992 (Box 21, Folder 4)
  - Naval Association of Australia, Ballina Sub-section, H.M.A.S. Scuttlebutt, Summer 1995/96 (Box 21, Box 5)
  - Pacific Ship and Shore Newsletter, February 1995, March 1995 (Box 21, Folder 6)
  - U.S. Naval Training Station, Great Lakes Bulletin, 1940. (Box 21, Folder 7)
  - U.S. Naval Training Station, Newport Recruit, August 16, 1930. (Box 21, Folder 8)
  - WWII Naval Journal, 1992-1993. (Box 21, Folder 9)
- ARTICLES, 1941-2000
  Articles are arranged alphabetically by title. In many cases, the entire magazine or newsletter that the article may be found in is in the folder.
  - The American Flag After Three and One Half Years undated. (Box 21, Folder 10)
  - The Battle of the Java Sea, Sea Classics, March 1992 (photocopy) (Box 21, Folder 11)
  - The Battle of Sunda Strait, Naval History, Spring 1992 (photocopy) (Box 21, Folder 12)
  - The Battle of Sunda Strait and the Survivor, undated (photocopy). (Box 21, Folder 13)
  - The Bridge Over The River Kwae: A Grim Episode of World War II, Tourist Organization of Thailand (photocopy), August 1977. (Box 21, Folder 14)
  - Brown Room Houses Cruiser Memorabilia, The Extra, Summer 1981. (Box 21, Folder 15)
  - Building the Death Railway, The Retired Officer, October 1981 (photocopy) (Box 21, Folder 16)
  - The Chester Class Cruisers, undated (photocopy) (Box 21, Folder 17)
  - The City Ensures That the USS Houston Will Sail Again, Texas: Houston Chronicle Magazine, December 7, 1986 (Box 21, Folder 18)
  - Cruiser Houston Memorial Exhibit and the George R. Brown Room, Texas Libraries, Fall 1981. Donor: Otto Schwarz (Box 21, Folder 19)
  - Death of the Houston, American Legion Magazine, January 1951. (Box 21, Folder 20)
  - Death of the Houston,Time, March 11, 1946 (photocopy) (Box 21, Folder 21)
  - Dedication Held for Special Room, Library Newsletter, Summer 1981. Donor: Otto Schwarz (Box 21, Folder 22)
  - Escape from Java: The Real Story of Dr. Wassell, USN Series, 1994 (Box 21, Folder 23)
  - Expendables: The Retreat from Manila, Shipmate, August 1954 (Box 21, Folder 24)
  - The Fate of the Galloping Ghost, Reader’s Digest, December 1950 (Box 21, Folder 25)
  - For Want of a Plane, Shipmate, January/February 1984 (Box 21, Folder 26)
  - The Galloping Ghost, United States Naval Institute Proceedings, February 1949, with clipping, 1949 (Box 21, Folder 27)
  - The Galloping Ghost Comes of Age, Our Navy, March 1963 (photocopy). (Box 21, Folder 28)
  - The Galloping Ghost of the Java Coast, Port of Houston, November 1994. (Box 21, Folder 29)
  - Galloping Ghost Surrounded, World War II, undated (photocopy). (Box 21, Folder 30)
  - George Stoddard: A Houston Survivor, October 15, 1985. (Box 21, Folder 31)
  - The Heroic Houston's Last Stand, LifeDec. 21, 1962 (photocopy) (Box 21, Folder 32)
  - He Who Sees First Lives Longest, Naval History, July/August 1994 (Box 21, Folder 33)
  - Honoring the Past, Raymond Record, 1982. (Box 21, Folder 34)
  - Honor Roll, Our Navy, September 1942 (Box 21, Folder 35)
  - Houston I Begins An Heroic Tradition, Shipyard Bulletin, November 1962. (Box 21, Folder 36)
    Donor: Donald Royce
  - Houston Replaces “Houston's” Losses, Life Magazine, June 15, 1942 (photocopy). (Box 21, Folder 37)
  - The Houston's Last Battles, Shipmate, May 1946. (Box 21, Folder 38)
  - The Houston's Last Fight, parts 1 and 2, Our Navy, December 1945. (Box 21, Folder 39)
  - Invasion Fleet Challenged, World War II, undated (photocopy). (Box 22, Folder 1)
  - Jap Fleet Defeats Ours – In a Jap Story, Our Navy, February 1942 (photocopy) (Box 22, Folder 2)
  - Java Sea: Allied Debacle, War at Sea: The Rising Sun in the Pacific, undated (photocopy). (Box 22, Folder 3)
  - The Java Sea Battles: February-March 1942, undated (Box 22, Folder 4)
  - The Legacy of the USS Houstons: A Case of Unparalleled Patriotism, Texas: Houston Chronicle Magazine, December 9, 1979 (Box 55, Folder 6)
  - Liberators on the Kwai, Aerospace Historian, June 1983 (Box 22, Folder 5)
  - The Modified Leander Class, HMAS Perth undated (Box 22, Folder 6)
  - One of Nine, 1982. (Box 22, Folder 7)
  - Other Allied ships, 1941-1997 (includes photocopies) (Box 22, Folder 8)
  - Prisoners of War Rescued from Torpedoed Japanese Transport, Statement by Acting Prime Minister [Australia], November 17, 1944 (Box 22, Folder 9)
  - Proudly She Sailed: The Saga of the USS Houston, in Aldus galley proof, [ca. 1980] (Box 22, Folder 10)
  - Remember the Houston, Cavalier, undated (Box 22, Folder 11)
  - Sacrifices Must Be Made, Proceedings, February 1992 (photocopy) (Box 22, Folder 12)
  - Saga of Two Stout Ships, [Shipyard Bulletin?], undated (Box 22, Folder 13)
  - Second To None, 1945. Donor: Eugene Crispi (Box 22, Folder 14)
  - Ship of the Month, USS Houston, USCS Log, February 2000. (Box 22, Folder 15)
  - ’Silver Anvil’ Goes to Naval Reserve Unit, Sea Power, August 1984. (Box 22, Folder 16)
  - Splash Heard ‘Round the World and Capturing the Moment, Masthead, Newport News Shipbuilding, 1981. (Box 22, Folder 17)
  - Time Ran Out for USS Houston, Ye Olde Dutch Mill, June 1983, reprinted from Houston Post, February 1983. (Box 22, Folder 18)
  - A Tribute to Dr. Han Hekking, Congressional Record, November 18, 1983 (photocopy), with clipping. (Box 22, Folder 19)
    Donor: Leonard “Dutch” Kooper
  - Tribute to Texas and Houston (by Secretary of the Navy Frank Knox), [ca. December 1942] (Box 22, Folder 20)
  - United States Strategic Bombing Survey (Pacific), The Japanese Invasion of the Philippines, the Dutch East Indies, and Southeast Asia, from The Campaigns of the Pacific War, 1946 (photocopy). (Box 22, Folder 21)
  - USS Houston AK-1, CA-30, and CL-81 from Dictionary of American Naval Fighting Ships, 1968 (photocopy). (Box 22, Folder 22)
  - USS Houston (CA-30) - Pride of the Asiatic Fleet, July 13, 1994. (Box 22, Folder 23)
  - USS Houston (CA-30), Military, July 1993 (Box 22, Folder 24)
  - The War Cruise of the USS Houston, undated (photocopy). (Box 22, Folder 25)